Finding Aid for Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (University of Michigan) records, 1985-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (University of Michigan) records 1985-2009
University of Michigan. Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center.
1 linear foot
2012122 Bimu 2
Program founded in 1986 to increase campus awareness of sexual assault and provide counseling and education services to sexual assault victims and the larger campus community. Records include correspondence, proposals, reports, survey samples, and topical files
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred by the Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (donor no. 8587 ) in several accessions, beginning in 1997.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The records are open without restriction.
The origins of the Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (SAPAC) lie in a January 1985 student sit-in in the office of the Vice-President for Student Services to address women's safety on campus and promote the opening of a rape crisis center. In May of that year, University of Michigan executive officers approved $75,000 for an anti-assault program. In February 1986, SAPAC opened as a division of Student Services, with Julie Steiner serving as Coordinator and the offices located in the Union. Its mission was to "provide counseling, education, information, and assistance to assault survivors, students, and the university community." Some of SAPAC's early activities included training of peer educators to lead workshops, presentations to new students and parents during Summer Orientation to increase awareness of sexual assault issues, organization of Sexual Assault Awareness Week, formation of SAFEWALK, a walking escort program, and the hiring of a counselor to provide counseling and advocacy services to sexual assault survivors. In 1988, SAPAC launched a 24-hour Crisis Line providing support and counseling to survivors. In 2008, in conjunction with SafeHouse Center in Ann Arbor and with funding from the U.S. Department of Justice's Office of Violence Against Women, SAPAC developed a nationally-recognized toolkit called "Striving for Justice: A Toolkit for Judicial Resolution Officers on College Campuses" to increase awareness of sexual assault issues among individuals working in student conflict resolution. SAPAC held a 25th anniversary concert in October 2011 and a weekend-long anniversary celebration in April 2012.
Source: Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center. "Our History." Accessed July 25, 2012. http://sapac.umich.edu/article/158.
The Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (SAPAC) records have been divided into six series: Correspondence, Proposals, Reports, Statistics, Surveys, and Topical.
Subjects:
U-M Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center.; Rape--Prevention.; Sex crimes--Prevention.; Sexual harassment in universities and colleges--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Crimes against.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series consists of a 1988 form letter to friends of the Center, memos to SAPAC staff, and a March 1993 update for SAPAC volunteers.
  - Friends of the Center 1988 (Box 1)
  - Memos 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Volunteer Update 1993 (Box 1)
- Proposals
  The Proposals series includes early proposals for the establishment of the Center, a 1990-1991 budget proposal, a proposal to expand SAPAC's library, and an application to receive funds under the terms of the Victim of Crime Act.
  - Budget Proposal 1990-1991, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Implementation of the Proposal for the Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center 1986 (Box 1)
  - A Proposal to Expand SAPAC's Library 1993 (Box 1)
  - U of M Rape Crisis Center 1985 (Box 1)
  - Victim of Crime Act (VOCA) Grant Application 1993 (Box 1)
- Reports
  The Reports series is composed of reports documenting the Center's activities and accomplishments. Some of the key reports in this series include early reports to the Office of Student Services from 1987 to 1989 and a 2001 review of the program conducted by the Campus Safety and Security Advisory Committee.
  - Date Rape Workshop 2004 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation Report for the SAPAC Peer Education Freshmen Workshops: 2008-2009, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Freshmen Workshops 2004 (Box 1)
  - General Volunteer Program Reports 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Main Office Component Winter 1992 Evaluation, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Peer Education Program Term End Reports 1997-2004 (Box 1)
  - Rape Prevention Month Winter 1991 Report, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Report on a Review of the University of Michigan Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center, Submitted by the Campus Safety and Security Advisory Committee, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Reports to Dean of Students Office 1994 (Box 1)
  - Reports to Office of Student Services 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - SAPAC Accomplishments 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Self-Assessment 1995 (Box 1)
  - Year End Report 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Statistics
  - 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1990-1997, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Surveys
  - CA Workshop 2005 (Box 1)
  - Domestic/Dating Violence Workshop 2004 (Box 1)
  - Frosh Workshop 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Men's Workshop 2003 (Box 1)
  - Peer Education Training Survey 2003 (Box 1)
  - Sexual Assault Workshop 2003 (Box 1)
  - Sexual Harassment Workshop 2004 (Box 1)
  - Volunteer Survey, circa early 2000s (Box 1)
  - Volunteer Training Survey 2008 (Box 1)
- Topical
  - Ann Arbor Mayor's Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women 1997 (Box 1)
  - Budget 1989 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Program 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Dating Violence Prevention Program 1994, undated (Box 1)
  - External Programmatic Review 1996 (Box 1)
  - Flint Program 1993 (Box 1)
  - Greek Life Peer Education Project 2001 (Box 1)
  - Housing/Residence Education 1996 (Box 1)
  - Men's Program 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Presentation Scripts 1985-1994 (Box 1)
  - Referral System 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - SAPAC/Athletic Department Collaboration on Violence against Women 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sexual Assault Protocol 1994 (Box 1)
  - Tamara Williams Memorial Lecture, circa early 2000s (Box 1)
  - Workshops
    - Athletic Team Training Evaluations 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - General 1991-1993, undated (Box 1)